Guide to the George P. Garrett Papers, 1929-2008 (bulk 1960-2000)
George P. Garrett papers 1929-2008 (bulk 1960-2000)
Garrett, George P., 1929-2008
268 Linear Feet 177,929 Items
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
George P. Garrett (1929-2008) was a poet, editor, author, and professor of English.
The papers of George P. Garrett span the years 1929 to 2000 with the bulk of the material being dated between 1960 and 1990. The papers were initially collected and assembled by author, bibliographer, and publisher Stuart T. Wright. Wright published a number of Garrett's works at his Palaemon Press and also assembled the Stuart Wright Bibliographic Collection of George Garrett (see related materials held by the Rubenstein Library). Additional materials were received by the Library directly from George Garrett. The papers document Garrett's literary career as an author of novels, short stories, poetry, and dramatic works (including filmscripts) and the tremendous influence he had as an English professor and an editor on an entire generation of writers, particularly in the South. Correspondence with numerous authors, publishers, and educators offers much information about the history of 20th-century Southern literature, publishing, and literary education. The collection is divided into the Writings Series (with subseries of Writings by Garrett, Writings Edited by Garrett, Writings by Others, and Proofs); the Correspondence Series (with 5 subseries of alphabetically and chronologically arranged correspondence); the Audiovisual Material Series; and the Miscellaneous Papers Series.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Also, some materials in this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of George P. Garrett were collected and assembled by Stuart T. Wright and were acquired as part of the Leona Bowman Carpenter Collection of English and American Literature by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library of Duke University in 1993. Subsequent additions were received as gifts from George Garrett and others between 1993 and 2008.
Biographical Note
1929, June 11 Born in Florida to George Palmer Garrett and Rosalie Toomer Garrett
1946 Graduated from Sewanee Military Academy
1948-1949 Studied at Columbia University
1952 Received BA from Princeton University
1952 Married Susan Parrish Jackson
1953-1955 Served in United States Army, including tour of duty with Occupation Forces in Trieste
1956 Received MA from Princeton University
1956-1960 Assistant Professor, Wesleyan University
1958-1971 U.S. Poetry Editor, Transatlantic Review, Rome, London, New York City
1961-1962 Visiting Lecturer, Rice University
1962-1967 Associate Professor, University of Virginia
1963-1968 Contemporary Poetry Series Editor, University of North Carolina Press
1964-1965 Writer-in-Residence, Princeton University
1967-1971 Professor of English and Director of Writing Program, Hollins College
1970- Contributor Editor, Contempora, Atlanta, Ga.
1971- Contributor Editor, The Film Journal, New York City, N.Y.
1971-1973 Professor of English and Writer-in-Residence, University of South Carolina
1972- Co-editor, Worksheet, Columbia, S.C.
1974-1976 Senior Fellow, Council of the Humanities, Princeton University
1976-1977 Adjunct Professor, School of the Arts, Columbia University
1978-1979 Writer-in-Residence, University of Michigan
1979-1980 Professor of English, Bennington College
1981 Eminent Scholar, Virginia Military Institute
1982-1984 Professor of English, University of Michigan
1984- Henry Hoyns Professor of Creative Writing, University of Virginia
1985 Received Ph.D. from Princeton University
2002-2006 Poet Laureate of Virginia
May 25, 2008 Died
Collection Overview
The papers of George P. Garrett span the years 1929 to 2000 with the bulk of the material being dated between 1960 and 1990. The papers were initially collected and assembled by author, bibliographer, and publisher Stuart T. Wright. Wright published a number of Garrett's works at his Palaemon Press and also assembled the Stuart Wright Bibliographic Collection of George Garrett (see related materials held by the Rubenstein Library). Additional materials were received by the Library directly from George Garrett.
The collection primarily documents Garrett's literary career as an author of novels, short stories, poetry, and dramatic works (including filmscripts) and the tremendous influence he had as an English professor and an editor on an entire generation of writers, particularly in the South. Correspondence with numerous authors, publishers, and educators offers much information about the history of 20th-century Southern literature, publishing, and literary education. The collection is divided into the Writings Series (with subseries of Writings by Garrett, Writings Edited by Garrett, Writings by Others, and Proofs); the Correspondence Series (with 5 subseries of alphabetically and chronologically arranged correspondence); the Audiovisual Material Series; and the Miscellaneous Papers Series.
The Alphabetical Correspondence Subseries: Group A contains letters from numerous contemporary American authors, among them Madison Smartt Bell, who wrote regarding the progress of his fiction, his experience with publishers and literary agents, and his interview with Garrett for Paris Review; and Fred Chappell, whose letters provide commentary on his own works The Inkling and Dagon as well as praise for Garrett's Death of the Fox, The Magic Striptease, and Welcome to the Medicine Show. The Writings by Others Subseries contains Bell's interview with Garrett, in which Garrett discusses his writing process, and critical essays by Fred Chappell (including one on Garrett's The Stranger in the Mirror and one on the work of Sylvia Wilkinson). The Proofs Subseries contains a proof of Reynolds Price's Collected Stories, with brief comments by Garrett.
Garrett's own literary career is documented throughout the collection. The Writings by Garrett Subseries contains manuscripts, typescripts, notes, and drafts of his work, some of it bearing notes for revision. The Chronological Correspondence Subseries contains letters in which Garrett wrote about his works in progress and letters from friends and publishers regarding his work. The comments of noted literary figures regarding Garrett's work frequently appear in letters in the Alphabetical Correspondence Subseries: Group A. This series also affords researchers a detailed view of literary criticism and support exchanged between Garrett and the many authors represented in the collection. His negotiations with publishers are best documented in the Alphabetical Correspondence Subseries: Group B. The Audiovisual Material Series contains some recordings of Garrett reading from his own work.
The Audiovisual Material Series, which contains many recordings of Garrett's lectures, classes, and addresses to groups of writers, students, and literary scholars, documents Garrett's teaching style and his ideas on the teaching of writing. Recordings of lectures and readings by many other well-known authors also appear in this series. Garrett's impact on his students and fellow authors is again visible in the Writings by Others Subseries, which consists of numerous manuscripts, typescripts, and drafts (some bearing notes by Garrett) of work sent to Garrett for commentary and revision.
The addition (Acc. 1998-0356) (5500 items, 15 linear feet; dated 1980-1998 [bulk 1995-1997]) further documents the life, career, and writing of the author and educator. It consists of audiotapes of various authors, including Garrett reading their works; a videocassette entitled The Great Gatsby; printed materials and writings, including published books, journals, drafts, and bound proofs; a large amount of personal and business correspondence; and manuscripts submitted to Garrett for comment.
The addition (Acc. 1999-0268) (1 item, 0.3 linear feet; dated [ca. 1996]) consists of a photocopied typescript of Garrett's novel The King of Babylon Shall Not Come Against You with handwritten annotations.
The addition (Acc. 1999-0379) (450 items, 0.6 linear feet; dated 1956-1972) is primarily comprised of incoming correspondence, chiefly professional; a number of writings are interfiled with or attached to letters. Also included are miscellaneous printed materials such as brochures and clippings.
The addition (Acc. 2000-0085) (9100 items, dated 1964-1999) further documents Garrett's literary career with additional manuscripts, often parts of or related to The King of Babylon Shall not Come Against You. There are audiotapes of readings by Garrett and others, literary correspondence, and clippings.
The addition (Acc. 2000-0303) (15 items, 1 linear foot; dated 1995-2000) documents some of Garrett's writing process and his direct comments in readings and on videotape. Included are page proofs and a revised typescript of The King of Babylon Shall Not Come Against You, a revised typescript of Entered From the Sun, 11 cassette tapes of readings and lectures presumably by Garrett, and a videotape entitled Writers - East of the Blue Ridge on which he is interviewed.
The addition (Acc. 2002-0034) (1 item, 1 lin. ft.; dated 2002) comprises an uncorrected page proof, with color cover, for Garrett's Going to See the Elephant: Pieces of a Writing Life. This accession is unprocessed and has been interfiled.
Additions (Acc. 2005-0067) (1875 items, 3.0 lin. ft.; dated 1990s-2003) and (Acc. 2004-0133) (2 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 2004) comprise manuscripts, drafts, notes, typescripts, and correspondence for Double Vision, The Year in Fiction, and Every Bitter Thing. Also includes typescripts, notes, holograph manuscripts, and typescripts with holograph corrections for essays, stories, and other writings; and a broadside of Garrett's poem, Luck's Shinning Child, printed for the 2004 Virginia Festival of the Book.
The addition (Acc. 2006-0090) (750 items, 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 2005-2006) contains proofs for Bad Man Blues and The King of Babylon Shall not Come Against You.; manuscripts for Godfather and several short stories; print materials including books and journals authored or edited by Garrett; 2 DVDs; and 12 computer diskettes. The content of these diskettes has been migrated to archival storage server. Closed pending processing.
The addition (Acc. 2007-0075)(5,400 items; 7.2 lin. ft.; dated 1971-2006) primarily contains drafts of Garrett's writings as typescripts and electronic files on diskettes. Also included are books and journals that feature his works and works of other authors; audiocassettes and CDs of interviews and readings by Garrett; and correspondence. Closed pending processing.
The addition (Acc. 2008-0181) (760 items; 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1999-2008) contains notes, research, and drafts of Garrett’s short story The Source, eventually renamed Thanksgiving. There are also some folders of correspondence, transcripts of interviews, and some audiovisual material including four audiocassette tapes and one DVD.
The addition (Acc. 2008-0271) (375 items; 0.6 lin. ft.; dated 1985-2008) contains correspondence; drafts and notes for poems and other projects, including an Armies of Occupation project; and copies of newspaper clippings and interviews with Garrett.
Addition (Acc. 2013-0168) (50 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1964-1972) comprises a file of letters to Garrett from those whose last names begin with the letter "P."
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Garrett, George P., 1929-.
Wilkinson, Sylvia, 1940-.
Chappell, Fred, 1936-.
Chappell, Fred, 1936- .; --Correspondence.
Price, Reynolds, 1933- .
Bell, Madison Smartt; --Correspondence.
American literature -- Southern States
Periodical editors -- United States -- Correspondence
Literature -- Study and teaching
Motion picture plays -- United States
Authors and publishers
Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence
Audiocassettes
Videocassettes
Related Material
Stuart Wright Bibliographic Collection of George Garrett, 1951-1993 and undated
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Writings Series, 1957-1996 and undated
  The Writings Series is divided into four subseries: Writings by Garrett, Writings Edited by Garrett, Writings by Others, and Proofs.
  - Writings by Garrett Subseries, 1957-1996 and undated
    Manuscripts, typescripts, and drafts of Garrett's published works, some bearing notations by Garrett. Categories include: Monographs (arranged chronologically in order of publication date of work), Dramatic Works and Short Stories (arranged alphabetically by title), Reviews (arranged alphabetically by the name of the author of the work being reviewed), Literary Essays and Biographies (arranged alphabetically by title), and Miscellaneous Writings and fragments (unarranged).
    - Monographs
      - 1957, King of the Mountain, (11 folders) (Box WG 1)
      - 1958, Sleeping Gypsy, (6 folders)
      - 1959, The Finished Man, (7 folders)
      - 1961, Abraham's Knife, (8 folders)
      - 1961, In the Briar Patch, (13 folders)
      - 1961, Which Ones are the Enemy?, (3 folders)
      - 1964, Cold Ground Was My Bed Last Night, (25 folders) (Box WG 2)
      - 1965, Do, Lord, Remember Me, (7 folders)
      - 1965, Do, Lord, Remember Me, (32 folders) (Box WG 3)
      - 1965, Do, Lord, Remember Me, (7 folders) (Box WG 4)
      - 1967, For a Bitter Season, (40 folders)
      - 1971, Death of the Fox, (7 folders)
      - 1971, Death of the Fox, (40 folders) (Box WG 5)
      - 1971, Death of the Fox, (42 folders) (Box WG 6)
      - 1971, Death of the Fox, (39 folders) (Box WG 7)
      - 1971, Death of the Fox, (18 folders) (Box WG 8)
      - 1971, Death of the Fox 43 folders) (Box WG 9)
      - 1973, The Magic Striptease, (29 folders) (Box WG 10)
      - 1978, Welcome to the Medicine Show, (8 folders)
      - 1981, Luck's Shining Child, (9 folders)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (50 folders) (Box WG 11)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (23 folders) (Box WG 12)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (43 folders) (Box WG 13)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (51 folders) (Box WG 14)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (38 folders) (Box WG 15)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (17 folders) (Box WG 16)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (36 folders) (Box WG 17)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (65 folders) (Box WG 18)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (27 folders) (Box WG 19)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (66 folders) (Box WG 20)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (49 folders) (Box WG 21)
      - 1983, The Succession: Elizabeth and James, (21 folders) (Box WG 22)
      - 1984, James Jones, (14 folders)
      - 1984, James Jones, (16 folders) (Box WG 23)
      - 1985, An Evening Performance, (24 folders) (Box WG 24)
      - 1985, Life with Kim Novak is Hell, (24 folders)
      - 1985, Life with Kim Novak is Hell, (21 folders) (Box WG 25)
      - 1986, Poison Pen, (34 folders)
      - 1986, Poison Pen, (2 folders) (Box WG 26)
      - 1988, Understanding Mary Lee Settle, (17 folders)
      - 1988, Understanding Mary Lee Settle, (1 folder) (Box WG 27)
      - 1990, Entered from the Sun, (20 folders)
      - 1990, Entered from the Sun, (23 folders) (Box WG 28)
      - 1990, Entered from the Sun, (33 folders) (Box WG 29)
      - 1990, Entered from the Sun, (30 folders) (Box WG 30)
      - 1990, Entered from the Sun, (3 folders) (Box WG 31)
      - 1992, My Silk Purse and Yours, (7 folders)
      - 1992, Sorrows of Fat City, (1 folder)
      - 1992, Whistling in the Dark, (9 folders)
      - 1992, Whistling in the Dark, (18 folders) (Box WG 32)
      - 1994, The Old Army Game, (15 folders)
      - 1996, King of Babylon, (3 folders)
    - Dramatic Works
      - The Acting Lesson, (1 folder) (Box WG 33)
      - Ajax, (1 folder)
      - Alexander the Great, (2 folders)
      - And So Love Came to Alfred Zeer, (2 folders)
      - The Architect, (1 folder)
      - Assassins, (1 folder)
      - The Best Man, (1 folder)
      - The Binge, (11 folders)
      - Charade, (1 folder)
      - Children of the Dark Gods, (1 folder)
      - Cold Ground Was My Bed Last Night, (3 folders)
      - Daughter of the Dark Gods, (1 folder)
      - Day of Reckoning, (2 folders)
      - Don't Take No for an Answer, (3 folders)
      - Do You Remember the Time in Florida?, (2 folders)
      - Elizabeth and Delancey, (1 folder) (Box WG 34)
      - Enchanted Ground, (8 folders)
      - The Entrepreneur, (1 folder)
      - The Farmer in the Dell, (1 folder)
      - Flesh, (1 folder)
      - Frankenstein Meets the Space Monster, (7 folders)
      - Futura, (2 folders)
      - Garden Spot, U.S.A., (8 folders)
      - Gentleman from Georgia, (1 folder)
      - Good Friday, (1 folder) (Box WG 35)
      - The Hussar, (1 folder)
      - King of the Mountain, (2 folders)
      - Knight of the Kitchen, (2 folders)
      - Little Tune for a Steel String Guitar, (1 folder)
      - Magic City, (11 folders)
      - Magic Striptease, (2 folders)
      - Man without a Figleaf, (1 folder)
      - The Moth, (1 folder)
      - My Brother, Death, (1 folder)
      - My Picture Left in Scotland, (1 folder)
      - Noise of Strangers, (1 folder)
      - Old Knight, (1 folder)
      - 3 Myths from Ovid, (1 folder)
      - The Playground, (1 folder)
      - Prism, (1 folder)
      - Sir Slob and the Princess, (4 folders)
      - Snead and Frumley, (1 folder)
      - Song of a Drowning Sailor, (1 folder)
      - Time of Assassins, (1 folder)
      - Unfortunate Lover, (1 folder)
      - Which Ones are My Enemies?, (1 folder)
      - The Word, the Flesh, and a Smiling Girl, (1 folder)
      - Wounded Soldier, (1 folder)
      - Young Lovers, (2 folders)
    - Short Stories
      - The Active Garden, (1 folder) (Box WG 36)
      - Al, (1 folder)
      - Alpha, (1 folder)
      - And So Love Came to Alfred Zeer, (1 folder)
      - Another Abdication, (1 folder)
      - Arlette of Falaise, (1 folder)
      - As travellers from far places..., (1 folder)
      - Atom Christ, (1 folder)
      - Atos, (1 folder)
      - A Bad Boy, (1 folder)
      - Beach Party, (1 folder)
      - Bedtime Story, (1 folder)
      - Bennington, (1 folder)
      - Black Man, (1 folder)
      - Big Tall Ghost of F. Scott Fitzgerald, (1 folder)
      - Blow Out the Candle, (2 folders)
      - Blues, (1 folder)
      - The Bride, (1 folder)
      - Casual Magnolia, (1 folder)
      - The Cave, (1 folder)
      - Clyde Crabtree, (1 folder)
      - The Coin, (1 folder)
      - Color of a Sigh..., (1 folder)
      - Conshoken, (1 folder)
      - Conversation at Princeton Station, (1 folder)
      - Days of Our Lives..., (2 folders)
      - Dear John, (2 folders)
      - Dear Ralph Ellison, (1 folder)
      - Death of Garden Spot, (1 folder)
      - Decline and Fall of Dave O'Hara, (2 folders)
      - A Dirty Story, (1 folder)
      - Divine Wind, (1 folder)
      - Dixie Dreamland, (2 folders)
      - Don't Look Now Mother..., (1 folder)
      - Drink Muddy Water, (1 folder)
      - Entered from the Sun, (1 folder)
      - Epigram, (1 folder)
      - Epigraph #2, (1 folder)
      - Epilogue, (1 folder)
      - Escapes, (3 folders)
      - The Experiment, (1 folder)
      - Fable of the Times, (1 folder)
      - Fabliaux (, (1 folder)
      - Faiths are a forest..., (1 folder)
      - Farewell All Joys, (1 folder)
      - Feeling Good, Feeling Fine, (1 folder)
      - Figure of Speech, (1 folder)
      - Fin de Siecle, (1 folder)
      - Final Tape of Dr. Wisdom, (1 folder)
      - Flamenco Dancer, (1 folder)
      - Flash Cards, (2 folders)
      - Floogie, (2 folders)
      - for 'Milkshake', (1 folder)
      - from 'Lives of Poets ', (1 folder)
      - Genius Baby, (1 folder)
      - Gentleman from Georgia, (1 folder)
      - Gesture of Circe, (1 folder)
      - Ghosts, (1 folder)
      - Girl with the Marble Thigh, (5 folders)
      - Glass Jaw, (1 folder)
      - Good-bye to the Ice Cream Kingdom, (1 folder)
      - Good Evening..., (1 folder)
      - Good Fridays, (1 folder)
      - Guitar Themes, (1 folder)
      - Harrangue by a Clown..., (1 folder)
      - Here Comes the Bride, (3 folders)
      - The Hollins Conference, (1 folder)
      - Hounds of Actaeon, (1 folder)
      - Houston, (1 folder)
      - How Can You Tell...?, (1 folder)
      - Hunter's View, (1 folder)
      - I read the death of Whitman's dream, (1 folder)
      - I Say It's Spinach, (2 folders)
      - I stand on the threshold..., (1 folder)
      - I Will Sing for You Sweetly, (1 folder)
      - If the Phone Rings, Don't Answer, (1 folder)
      - In a Bad Time, (1 folder)
      - In the Time of Tall Kings, (1 folder)
      - Inch by Inch, (1 folder)
      - Inertia, (1 folder)
      - Intoxicants..., (1 folder)
      - Invention of Canasta, (1 folder)
      - It is the Winter Wind (, (1 folder)
      - It's like Groundhog Day..., (1 folder)
      - J.T. writes another poem..., (1 folder)
      - Justice, (1 folder)
      - The Lady Diana Takes Tea, (1 folder)
      - Land of the Magic Forest, (1 folder)
      - The Last Magician, (1 folder)
      - The Legacy and Berrying, (1 folder)
      - Leon Waddell, (1 folder)
      - Lesson for Today, (1 folder)
      - Letter to a Scholar, (1 folder)
      - Linz, Austria, (1 folder)
      - Little Song, (1 folder)
      - Little ugly grey bird..., (1 folder)
      - Lions are Everywhere, (1 folder)
      - Lonely Grave, (1 folder)
      - Long and Short of It, (4 folders)
      - Look Who's Talking Now, (1 folder)
      - The Lost Brother..., (1 folder)
      - Madman Charley..., (1 folder) (Box WG 37)
      - Mama and Mt. Parnassus, (1 folder)
      - Martin Nettleton, (1 folder)
      - Matadors, (1 folder)
      - Message Found in a Bottle, (1 folder)
      - Montreal Project, (1 folder)
      - The Monument, (2 folders)
      - Moon Girl, (1 folder)
      - Morning, (1 folder)
      - Mosaic, (1 folder)
      - My Pretty Birdie..., (1 folder)
      - Naked and Bare as Truth, (1 folder)
      - Neighbors, (1 folder)
      - New American Poets, (1 folder)
      - Not from vintage..., (2 folders)
      - Now in the tranquil, blackest hours..., (1 folder)
      - O, in them Long, Hot Summer Days, (2 folders)
      - Oh Muse, Speak to Me!, (1 folder)
      - Old Love Song, (1 folder)
      - Old man, we are ordained to meet..., (1 folder)
      - One More Tatoo, (2 folders)
      - One Winter Night, (1 folder)
      - Organ Music, (1 folder)
      - Other Side of the Corn, (1 folder)
      - Our Lady Godiva, (1 folder)
      - Our River Trips, (1 folder)
      - Part II: Four Fabliaux, (1 folder)
      - Ploughshares, (1 folder)
      - The Plumed Hat, (1 folder)
      - Portrait of the Artist as a Young Irishman, (1 folder)
      - Prelude to an Interview, (1 folder)
      - Princeton: A Hole in My Shoe, (1 folder)
      - Prism, (1 folder)
      - Programme..., (1 folder)
      - Pursuit, (2 folders)
      - Quarto of the 16th Letter, (1 folder)
      - The Rare Unicorn, (2 folders)
      - A Record as Long as Your Arm, (1 folder)